W. L. McAtee Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
W. L. McAtee Papers 1803-1963 1900-1960
MSS31849
McAtee, W. L. (Waldo Lee), 1883-1962
40,000 items
116 containers
46.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Biologist and ornithologist. Correspondence, research and writings, field notes and notebooks, poetry, prose, reviews, and other avocational writings, calendars, diaries, memorabilia, scrapbook, wills, and printed matter chiefly documenting McAtee's career as a biologist and ornithologist at the United States Bureau of Biological Survey and its successor, the United States Fish and Wildlife Service, and as curator of Hemiptera at the Smithsonian Institution.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Banta, Arthur M. (Arthur Mangun), 1877-1946--Correspondence.; Beal, F. E. L. (Foster Ellenborough Lascelles), 1840-1916--Correspondence.; Bloch, Donald Beaty, -1984--Correspondence.; Buchanan, Lee L. (Lee La Forest), 1893- --Correspondence.; Chapman, Frank M. (Frank Michler), 1864-1945--Correspondence.; Combs, Josiah Henry, 1886-1960--Correspondence.; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882.; Fisher, A. K. (Albert Kenrick), 1856-1948--Correspondence.; Gabrielson, Ira Noel, 1889- --Correspondence.; Holt, Ernest G.--Correspondence.; Hood, J. Douglas (Joseph Douglas), 1889-1966--Correspondence.; Kinsey, Alfred C. (Alfred Charles), 1894-1956--Correspondence.; Lloyd, Hoyes--Correspondence.; Malleis, Harry--Correspondence.; Malloch, John Russell, 1875- --Correspondence.; McAtee family--Correspondence.; McAtee, W. L. (Waldo Lee), 1883-1962.; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956--Correspondence.; Preble, Edward Alexander, 1871-1957--Correspondence.; Shoemaker, Henry W., 1880-1958.--Correspondence.; Stoddard, Herbert L.--Correspondence.; Terres, John K.--Correspondence.; Wade, Joseph Sanford, 1880- --Correspondence.; Warnick, Florence--Correspondence.; Wood, Casey A. (Casey Albert), 1856-1942--Correspondence.
Organizations
Smithsonian Institution.; U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service.; United States. Bureau of Biological Survey.
Subjects
Animals--Washington (D.C.); Birds--Food.; Botanists--Autographs.; Entomologists--Autographs.; Evolution (Biology); Hemiptera.; Insects--Washington (D.C.); Mammalogists--Autographs.; Natural history--Washington (D.C.); Natural selection.; Ornithologists--Autographs.; Ornithology.; Plants--Washington (D.C.); Scientists.
Occupations
Biologists.; Ornithologists.
Acquisition Information
The papers of W. L. McAtee, biologist and ornithologist, were given to the Library of Congress by McAtee between 1942 and 1956. Additional material was received from John K. Torres in 1963, Marie Halun Bloch in 1989, and Robert McAtee in 1991.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of W. L. McAtee are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1883, Jan. 21 Born, Jalapa, Grant County, Ind.
1903 Assistant biological expert, Division of Biological Survey, Agriculture Department
1904 A.B., Indiana University, Bloomington, Ind.
1904 1916 Assistant biologist, Bureau of Biological Survey, Agriculture Department
1906 A.M., biology, Indiana University, Bloomington, Ind. Married Fannie Eldridge Lawson (divorced 1939)
1916 1921 Assistant biologist in charge of economic ornithology, Bureau of Biological Survey, Agriculture Department
1918 Published, A Sketch of the Natural History of the District of Columbia (Washington, D.C.: [Press of H. L. and J. B. McQueen]. 142 pp.)
1920 1947 Acting curator of Hemiptera, National Museum, Smithsonian Institution
1921 1934 Assistant biologist in charge of food habits research, Bureau of Biological Survey, Agriculture Department
1934 1940 Technical advisor, office of the chief, Bureau of Biological Survey, Agriculture Department
1937 1942 Editor, Journal of Wildlife Management
1939 Published Wildfowl Food Plants (Ames, Iowa: Collegiate Press, Inc. 141 pp.)
1940 1947 Technical advisor, Fish and Wildlife Service, Interior Department
1956 Published privately A Review of the Nearctic Viburnum (Chapel Hill, N.C. 125 pp.)
1962, Jan. 7 Died, Chapel Hill, N.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Waldo Lee McAtee (1883-1962) span the years 1803-1963, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1900-1960. The collection covers the full extent of McAtee's professional career at the Bureau of Biological Survey of the Department of Agriculture and its successor agency the Fish and Wildlife Service of the Department of Interior. He was noted especially for his research on the food habits of birds. Series within the collection include Correspondence, Research and Writings File, Handwriting Collection, and Miscellany.
The Correspondence File includes letters exchanged with numerous professional colleagues in various scientific fields and reflects McAtee's wide-ranging interests in ornithology, entomology, botany, and conservation. Prominent and frequent correspondents include Arthur Mangun Banta, F. E. L. Beal, Donald Beaty Bloch, Lee L. Buchanan, Frank M. Chapman, Josiah Henry Combs, A. K. Fisher, Ira Noel Gabrielson, Ernest G. Holt, J. Douglas Hood, Alfred C. Kinsey, Hoyes Lloyd, Harry Malleis, H. L. Mencken, John Russell Malloch, Edward Alexander Preble, Henry W. Shoemaker, Herbert L. Stoddard, John K. Terres, Joseph Snford Wade, Florence Warnick, and Casey A. Wood. The file also contains correspondence with family members including McAtee's wife, Fannie E. McAtee, his brother, Morris McAtee, and his son, Robert B. McAtee.
The Research and Writings File contains McAtee's notes and background resources for his professional writings. Drafts and printed copies of his writings are rarely present since McAtee donated a large collection of his writings to the Rare Book Collection of the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. The files reflect the intersection of McAtee's major studies in ornithology, entomology, and botany. His focus on the feeding habits of birds sparked his studies and writings on insects and plants, and he served as curator of Hemiptera at the Smithsonian Institution for twenty-seven years.
Among the highlights of the Research and Writings File is a large group of material related to his observations of wildlife, insects, and flora in and around the District of Columbia which he used for his book, A Sketch of the Natural History of the District of Columbia. Also notable is a large group of notes and background material pertaining to evolution as well as to an unpublished manuscript titled "A Critique of Darwin." After thirty years of study in the food habits of birds and other topics, McAtee became convinced that Darwin's theory of natural selection was flawed. In an application to a publisher in 1947, McAtee wrote "Average, not fittest or superlative, individuals survive, so the process provides no motor for evolution; the moving force must be sought elsewhere than in the 'struggle for existence.'" Other significant files relate to McAtee's biographical notes on prominent scientists, a large collection of field trip notes, and a manuscript and notes for his privately published A Review of the Nearctic Viburnum.
In the 1940s McAtee collected handwriting samples of ornithologists, botanists, mammalogists, entomologists and other groups. His collection consists of fragments of correspondence, receipts, notes, envelopes, and other sources for examples of handwriting.
The Miscellany series includes records of the Bureau of Biological Survey containing correspondence, field reports, office memoranda, and a report on the early years of the bureau. Also included is a group of miscellaneous avocational writings by McAtee consisting of poetry, prose, reviews, and other works which, in many instances, were privately printed by McAtee. Calendars, diaries, memorabilia, a scrapbook, wills, and printed matter are also contained in the Miscellany.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is arranged in four series:
Correspondence, 1884-1962
Research and Writings File, 1803-1963
Handwriting Collection, 1847-1945
Miscellany, 1881-1961
Container List
- Correspondence, 1884-1962 (Box 1-44)
  Correspondence received and sent.
  Arranged as received into two groups: Set I includes material dated through 1929; Set II includes material from 1930 and thereafter. Arranged alphabetically within each set and chronologically thereunder.
  - Set I, 1884-1929, undated (Box 1)
    - Adams, Charles C., 1912-1927
    - Alexander, Charles P., 1915-1927
    - "A" miscellaneous, 1903-1929, undated, (2 folders)
    - Baker, Charles Fuller, 1923-1927, undated
    - Ball, Elmer Darwin, 1917-1928
    - Banks, Nathan, 1917-1929
    - Banta, Arthur Mangun, 1904-1925, (2 folders)
    - Barber, Harry Gardner, 1913-1929
    - Beal, Foster Ellenborough Lascelles and Mary Louise, 1903-1917, undated (Box 2)
    - Bergroth, Ernest Evald, 1919-1924
    - Britain, W. H., 1918-1927
    - "B" miscellaneous, 1900-1929, undated, (5 folders)
    - Chapman, Frank M., 1911-1926 (Box 3)
    - China, W. E., 1922-1928
    - Collinge, Walter E., 1913-1929, undated
    - "C" miscellaneous, 1900-1929, undated, (3 folders)
    - Davis, William T., 1912-1929
    - Deane, Ruthven, 1906-1929
    - Dozier, H. L., 1926-1929
    - Drake, Carl J., 1917-1929, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - "D" miscellaneous, 1905-1929, undated, (2 folders)
    - "E" miscellaneous, 1903-1929
    - Fisher, A. K., 1903-1929
    - Floyd, Bayard F., 1900-1926
    - Forbes, Stephen A., 1884-1925
    - Forbush, Edward Howe, 1909-1929
    - Frison, Theodore H., 1924-1929
    - Funkhouser, W. D., 1915-1927 (Box 5)
    - "F" miscellaneous, 1911-1929, (2 folders)
    - Gardner, Leon Lloyd and Margaret L., 1920-1929, undated
    - Greeley, John R., 1922-1929, undated
    - "G" miscellaneous, 1908-1929, undated, (2 folders)
    - Hahn, Walter L. and Alta M., 1903-1910, 1924
    - Harper, Francis, 1913-1929
    - Harper, Roland M., 1913-1929
    - Haseman, John D., 1904-1921
    - Hine, James S., 1916-1921, undated
    - Holt, Ernest G., 1914-1929, undated, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Hood, J. Douglas, 1914-1929
    - Howard, L. C., 1918-1929
    - Hungerford, H. B., 1918-1929
    - "H" miscellaneous, 1903-1929, (3 folders)
    - Irwin, William A., 1900-1921
    - Jaczewski, T., 1925-1929 (Box 7)
    - "J" miscellaneous, 1921-1929
    - Kalmbach, E. R., 1911-1927
    - Kennedy, Clarence H., 1903-1926
    - Knight, H. H., 1915-1929
    - "K" miscellaneous, 1908-1929
    - Lawson, Paul B., 1919-1929
    - Lloyd, Hoyes, 1922-1929
    - "L" miscellaneous, 1910-1929
    - Mabbott, Douglass C., 1917-1929 (Box 8)
    - Malleis, Harry, 1923-1928 See also Container 103, same heading
    - Malloch, John R., 1913-1921, (2 folders)
    - Metcalf, Franklin P., 1917-1921
    - Muir, Frederick, 1920-1929
    - "M" miscellaneous, 1900-1929, undated, (4 folders)
    - "N" miscellaneous, 1908-1929 (Box 9)
    - "O" miscellaneous, 1907-1928
    - Parshley, Howard M., 1915-1925
    - Phillips, John C., 1909-1929
    - Pierce, R. V., 1910-1920
    - "P" miscellaneous, 1901-1929, (2 folders)
    - "Q" miscellaneous, 1918-1929
    - Rice, James Henry, Jr., 1909-1929
    - Rowher, S. A., 1917-1928
    - "R" miscellaneous, 1900-1929, (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - Stoddard, Herbert L., 1922-1928
    - Stone, Witmer, 1912-1929
    - "S" miscellaneous, 1906-1929, (4 folders)
    - Taverner, P. A., 1905-1929 (Box 11)
    - "T" miscellaneous, 1900-1929
    - "U" miscellaneous, 1918-1929
    - Van Duzee, E. P., 1912-1929
    - "V" miscellaneous, 1918-1929
    - Wetmore, Alexander, 1912-1929
    - White, Jasper B., 1909-1929, (2 folders)
    - Wood, Casey A., 1917-1927 (Box 12)
    - "W" miscellaneous, 1904-1929, (3 folders)
    - "Y-Z" miscellaneous, 1905-1929
  - Set II, 1930-62, undated (Box 13)
    - Adams, Charles C., 1931-1944
    - Alexander, Charles P., 1935-1961
    - Alexander, W. B., 1930-1948
    - Allan, Philip F., 1939-1961
    - American Philosophical Society, 1943-1960
    - American Speech, 1943-1961
    - "A" miscellaneous, 1930-1961, (3 folders)
    - Bailey, Harold H., 1932-1961, (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - Baillie, James L., Jr., 1938-1951
    - Barber, Harry G., 1931-1960
    - Beale, Elsie V., 1935-1961
    - Benedict, Frances P., 1932-1954
    - Blake, Sidney F. and Doris, 1930-1960
    - Bloch, Donald Beaty
      - 1943-1950
      - 1951-1962, (4 folders) (Box 15)
    - Blocker, Emma G., 1937-1958, (2 folders) (Box 16)
    - Boulton, Rudyerd, 1938-1942
    - Bradley, F. W., 1951-1961
    - Buchanan, Lee L., 1931-1959, (2 folders)
    - Burton, E. Milby, 1937-1958
    - "B" miscellaneous, 1930-1961, (1 folder)
    - "B" miscellaneous, 1930-1961, (6 folders) (Box 17)
    - Cahalane, Victor H., 1948-1961 (Box 18)
    - Caminita, Ludwig, Jr., 1941-1961
    - Chambers, W. Lee, 1930-1956
    - Chapin, James P. and Ruth, 1930-1954
    - Chapman, Frank M., 1931-1945
    - Cheesman, William H., 1937-1960
    - China, W. E., 1930-1960
    - Clarke, C. H. D., 1937-1955
    - Collinge, Walter E., 1930-1948
    - Combs, Josiah Henry and Charlotte, 1945-1960, (2 folders)
    - Core, Earl L., 1937-1952 (Box 19)
    - Cottam, Clarence, 1932-1956
    - "C" miscellaneous, 1930-1961, (4 folders)
    - Davison, Verne E., 1934-1960
    - "D" miscellaneous, 1930-1961, (3 folders) (Box 20)
    - Edge, Rosalie, 1933-1952, undated, (4 folders)
    - Errington, Paul L., 1932-1958, (4 folders) (Box 21)
    - "E" miscellaneous, 1930-1961, (2 folders)
    - Fish and Wildlife Service, Interior Department, 1950-1961
    - Fisher, A. K., 1931-1948
    - Fleming, J. H., 1930-1939
    - Friedmann, Herbert, 1932-1949 (Box 22)
    - Frolke, Doris, 1951-1961, (2 folders)
    - "F" miscellaneous, 1930-1961, undated, (2 folders)
    - G. & C. Merriam Co., 1938-1961, (2 folders)
    - Gabrielson, Ira Noel, 1934-1961
    - Girard, George L., 1934-1958
    - Goethe, C. M., 1954-1960 (Box 23)
    - Graham, Edward H., 1938-1950
    - Grange, Wallace B., 1932-1960
    - Greene, Earle R., 1940-1960, (2 folders)
    - Grinnell, Joseph, 1930-1935
    - "G" miscellaneous, 1930-1961, (1 folder)
    - "G" miscellaneous, 1930-1961, (2 folders) (Box 24)
    - Hamilton, William J., Jr., 1931-1959
    - Hanley, Miles L., 1940-1946
    - Harper, Francis, 1933-1960
    - Harper, Roland M., 1931-1959, (2 folders)
    - Haseman, John D., 1933-1961
    - Henderson, Walter C., 1934-1946
    - Hickey, Joseph J., 1944-1959
    - Holt, Ernest G., 1930-1961, (3 folders) (Box 25)
    - Hood, J. Douglas, 1936-1960
    - Hornaday, William T., 1934-1936
    - Hotchkiss, Neil, 1946-1960, undated
    - Hyde, A. Sidney, 1931-1942
    - "H" miscellaneous, 1930-1961, undated, (1 folder)
    - "H" miscellaneous, 1930-1961, undated, (4 folders) (Box 26)
    - Indiana University, Bloomington, Ind., 1944-1961
    - "I" miscellaneous, 1936-1960
    - Jacoby, Thomas E., 1947-1961, (2 folders)
    - Jones, John C., 1940-1960 (Box 27)
    - "J" miscellaneous, 1930-1961
    - Kalmbach, E. R., 1931-1960, (2 folders)
    - Kennard, Frederic H., 1930-1937
    - Kennedy, Clarence H., 1931-1953
    - Kinsey, Alfred C., 1936-1956
    - Komarek, Edward V., 1935-1957
    - "K" miscellaneous, 1930-1961, (2 folders) (Box 28)
    - Lajos, Kaloczy, 1948-1961
    - Legman, G. Alexander, 1944-1960
    - Leopold, Aldo, 1930-1947
    - Lewis, Harrison F., 1941-1961
    - Library of Congress
      - 1935-1950, (2 folders)
      - 1951-1961 (Box 29)
    - Ligon, J. Stokely, 1934-1961, undated
    - Lincoln, Frederick C., 1931-1960
    - Lloyd, Hoyes, 1931-1961, (3 folders)
    - Lowery, George H., Jr., 1938-1961 (Box 30)
    - "L" miscellaneous, 1930-1961, (2 folders)
    - Mabbott, George W. and Orra, 1930-1959
    - Malloch, John R., 1934-1961
    - Mathews, M. M., 1943-1961
    - McAtee, Fannie E., 1932-1961, (2 folders) (Box 31)
    - McAtee, Morris, 1934-1961
    - McAtee, Robert B., 1940-1961, (2 folders)
    - McLeish, Ida C., 1947-1949
    - Mencken, H. L., 1939-1956, (2 folders)
    - Munro, James A., 1930-1958, (2 folders) (Box 32)
    - Murphy, Eugene E., 1937-1952
    - Murphy, Robert C., 1937-1960
    - Murray, J. J., 1936-1959
    - "M" miscellaneous, 1930-1961, (3 folders)
    - "M" miscellaneous, 1930-1961, (2 folders) (Box 33)
    - Neff, Johnson A., 1930-1961
    - Netting, M. Graham, 1936-1955
    - "N" miscellaneous, 1930-1961, (2 folders)
    - Osgood, Wilfred H., 1931-1944
    - "O" miscellaneous, 1930-1961
    - Payne, Fernandus, 1934-1956 (Box 34)
    - Pearl, Raymond, 1932-1940
    - Pearson, T. Gilbert, 1933-1942
    - Peters, James L., 1930-1952
    - Pough, Richard H., 1936-1949
    - Pound, Louise, 1943-1950
    - Preble, Edward A., 1932-1948
    - "P" miscellaneous, 1930-1961, (2 folders)
    - "Q" miscellaneous, 1931-1953
    - Read, Allen W., 1940-1960
    - Reid, Bessie M., 1933-1951 (Box 35)
    - Rush, Charles E., 1943-1958
    - Rush, Flora, 1950-1959
    - "R" miscellaneous, 1930-1961, (3 folders)
    - Sanderson, W. E., 1933-1944
    - Shoemaker, Henry W., 1936-1955, (2 folders) (Box 36)
    - Simmons, Perez, 1934-1961
    - Smith, Clarence F., 1940-1960
    - Snyder, Lester L., 1931-1961
    - Sprunt, Alexander, Jr., 1933-1958
    - Stevens, Ross O., 1932-1947
    - Stoddard, Herbert L.
      - 1932-1941
      - 1944-1961, (2 folders) (Box 37)
    - Stone, Witmer, 1930-1939, undated
    - Stoner, Dayton and Lillian, 1934-1960
    - Storer, Tracy I., 1930-1958
    - "S" miscellaneous, 1930-1961, (3 folders)
    - "S" miscellaneous, 1930-1961, (3 folders) (Box 38)
    - Taverner, Percy A., 1930-1947, (2 folders)
    - Terres, John K., 1935-1961, (3 folders) (Box 39)
    - Tomkins, Ivan R., 1945-1960
    - "T" miscellaneous, 1931-1961, (2 folders)
    - United States National Museum, Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C., 1942-1960
    - University of Chicago Press, 1944-1957
    - University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, N.C., 1954-1961
    - "U" miscellaneous, 1930-1960 (Box 40)
    - Van Dersal, William R., 1936-1960
    - Van Tyne, Josselyn, 1939-1947
    - "V" miscellaneous, 1930-1960
    - Wackerlin, Helena, 1949-1961
    - Wade, Douglas E., 1938-1957
    - Wade, Joseph Sanford, 1942-1961, (3 folders)
    - Walker, Ernest P., 1949-1959
    - Warnick, Florence (Box 41)
      - 1930-1957, (5 folders)
      - 1958-1961, (3 folders) (Box 42)
    - Weiss, Harry B., 1939-1961, (2 folders)
    - Westwood, Richard W., 1933-1961
    - Wetmore, Alexander, 1930-1961
    - Wilcoxson, Emily M., 1944-1955 (Box 43)
    - Wilson, George P., 1944-1961, (2 folders)
    - Wood, Casey A., 1931-1950
    - Wortman, Fred P., 1955-1961
    - Wright, Albert H., 1932-1945
    - "W" miscellaneous, 1930-1961, (2 folders)
    - "W" miscellaneous, 1930-1961, (2 folders) (Box 44)
    - "Y" miscellaneous, 1935-1961
    - Zimmer, John T., 1935-1950
    - Zoological Society of London, London, England, 1930
    - "Z" miscellaneous, 1934-1958
- Research and Writings File, 1803-1963 (Box 45-91)
  Notes, drafts, printed matter, correspondence, and other background material.
  Arranged alphabetically by title or topic and chronologically therein.
  - "An Account of Poisonous Sumachs, Rhus Poisoning, and Remedies Therefor," 1890-1940, undated, (2 folders) (Box 45)
  - "Account of The Pastime, A Washington Periodical, Largely of Natural History, Published in 1883-85," 1930-1932, undated
  - Agriculture Department
    - Bureau of Biological Survey
      - Appropriations, 1934, undated
      - Land planning objectives, 1939
      - Lectures, undated
      - Writings, 1937-1948, undated
    - Committee on Land Utilization, 1921-1927, 1943, undated
  - American Ornithologists' Union, 1929, 1938-1939, undated
  - "' Anting' by Birds," 1914, 1936-1938, undated (Box 46)
  - Ashbrook, Frank G., 1934
  - "Attracting birds"
    - Bird houses, 1922-1943, undated
    - General, 1911-1942, undated
    - Notes, 1922-1941, undated
    - Photographs, 1912-1929, undated
  - "Balds," (mountain pinnacles), circa 1948
  - Barrows, Walter Bradford, "Bird Notes for Horticulturists," lecture, 1893
  - Barton, Benjamin Smith See also Container 79, Rafinesque, Constantine S.
    - "Journals and Note-books of Benjamin Smith Barton," typescript, undated
      - Notes, 1945-1953, undated
  - Biographical notes
    - Bailey, Vernon, 1950, undated
    - Barber, Herbert Spencer, 1906, 1913, 1950-1951
    - Beal, Foster Ellenborough Lascelles (Box 47)
      - Notes, 1916-1917, 1943-1950, undated
      - Scrapbook, 1879-1927, undated
      - Writings, 1915, undated
    - Bureau of Biological Survey, staff, 1931, 1950-1951, undated
    - Cooke, Wells Woodbridge, 1950
    - Fisher, A. K., 1884-1927, 1950-1951, undated
    - Gaut, James H., 1905-1907, 1950
    - Gill, Theodore Nicholas, 1917, 1950
    - Heller, Edmund, 1947-1950
    - Henshaw, Henry Wetherbee, 1950
    - Herman, Otto, 1907, 1929-1933, undated
    - Hood, Joseph Douglas, 1951
    - Judd, Sylvester Dwight, 1941-1950, undated
    - McAtee, Waldo Lee, 1921-1963, undated
    - Merriam, C. Hart, 1909-1919, 1944, 1950, undated
    - Miscellaneous, 1948-1951, undated
    - Nelson, Edward Williams, 1921-1924, 1949-1950, undated (Box 48)
    - Oberholser, Harry Church, 1950
    - Osgood, Wilfred Hudson, 1950
    - Palmer, Theodore Sherman, 1950-1956, undated
    - Richmond, Charles Wallace, 1938-1942, undated
    - Schwarz, Eugene Amandus, 1951
    - Shannon, Raymond Corbett, 1917, 1940-1951, undated
    - Shufeldt, Robert Wilson, 1897, 1923, 1951, undated
    - Smith, Frank, 1942-1943
    - Trumbull, Gurdon, 1939-1940, undated
    - Wheeler, Charles Fay, 1907-1910, 1950
    - Wood, Casey Albert, 1942-1943
    - Xantus, Janos, 1898, 1930-1938, undated
  - Biological Abstracts, 1926-1943
  - "Bird Greens," 1947
  - Bird skins, identification of, circa 1903, circa 1913
  - Bird specimens collected, catalogs of, 1908-1920
  - Birds, lectures on, circa 1904, 1917-1918 (Box 49)
  - "Birds at Play," 1930-1947, undated
  - Birds distributing scale insects, undated
  - Birds feeding on dry fruits, 1935, (2 folders)
  - Birds feeding on fleshy fruits, 1935
  - "Birds Pickaback," 1944-1947, undated
  - Birth control, 1921-1936, undated
  - "The Biting Power of Ants," 1913, undated
  - "Call of the Whippoorwill," 1953, undated
  - Caprimulgidae-Micropodidae, 1907-1949, undated (Box 50)
  - Catesby's tropic bird, 1944, undated
  - "Census of Four Square Feet," circa 1907
  - Cheirodon annae, circa 1903
  - "Clean-up and 'Weeding' of Eastern Forests in Relation to Wildlife," 1929-1939, undated
  - Cleft Island, Md., 1918-1919, 1930, 1944, undated, (2 folders)
  - "Confusion of Eastern Caprimulgidae," 1948, undated
  - Conservation
    - Manuscripts, 1936-1947, undated
    - Notes, 1920-1950, undated
    - Textbook, proposed, 1944-1945
  - Cottam, Clarence, 1935-1937, undated
  - "A Critique of Darwinism" (Box 51)
    - Manuscript, undated, (2 folders)
    - Notes
      - Introduction, 1889-1948, undated, (3 folders)
      - Chapters (Box 52)
        - 1-7, 1898-1948, undated, (8 folders)
        - 8-11, 1892-1940, undated, (7 folders) (Box 53)
        - 12-16, 1881-1945, undated, (7 folders) (Box 54)
        - 17, 1896-1939, undated, (2 folders) (Box 55)
      - Appendixes
        - A-F, 1912-1948, undated, (6 folders)
        - G, 1933-1937, undated (Box 56)
      - Summary, undated
      - Miscellany, 1949, undated
  - Crows, 1893-1929, undated
  - "Cruelty in the Livestock Business," 1947
  - Currituck Sound, N.C., pollution of, 1929-1930, undated
  - "Departmental Natural History," 1923, undated
  - District of Columbia
    - Early bird records, 1918, 1951, undated